Guide to the Duane and Marian Waln Papers
Yale University Divinity School Library
Duane and Marian Waln Papers
1905-1962
RG 181
Yale University Divinity School Library
4
(8 boxes)
Journals, correspondence, and mission station "diaries" provide thorough and detailed documentation of work at the Chilesso Station of the ABCFM in Angola from 1905 to 1962. Also of interest in the collection are Duane Waln's papers on the Ovimbundu people and their customs, Umbundu language grammars and dictionaries, writings of the Walns relating to life on Chilesso Station and biographies of the native Christians. Duane and Marian ("Peggy") Waln were American missionaries in Angola from 1929 to 1962, serving primarily at the Chilesso Station of the West Central Africa Mission of the American Board of Commissioners for Foreign Missions. Duane Waln was involved in mission administrative work and evangelism. Peggy Waln's major project at Chilesso Station was founding and running a school for women, which had a home economics program.
Waln, Duane V.
Waln, Marian
Conditions Governing Access
Open to qualified researchers.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of the Waln family.
Biographical / Historical
The Walns were engaged in language study in Portugal from1928-1929 before going to the Chilesso Station of the ABCFM West Central Africa Mission, where they served from 1929 to 1962. Duane Victor Waln was acting director of the Currie Institute in Dondi for a brief period, but the Walns were primarily stationed at Chilesso.
Duane was engaged in evangelistic work, but also supervised construction and operation of the mission schools, hospital, and residences. Marian Ingram Waln (known as "Peggy") ran a Home Economics School for women and was much occupied by hospitality for mission colleagues and visitors. The Walns had two sons: Duane, Jr. and Robert.
Scope and Contents
The personal journals, letters, and station diaries contained in this collection provide exceptionally detailed documentation of the life and work of the Walns in Angola. Series I, Writings of Duane Waln, includes his journals from 1930 through 1962 plus material related to his graduate work while on furlough, and a series of biographical sketches of native Christians in Angola. The Writings of Marian ("Peggy") Waln in Series II also include biographical sketches of native women Christians as well as various drafts of talks and articles related to her work in Africa. Series III, Correspondence of Marian ("Peggy") Waln consists primarily of typescript carbons of letters written by her to family members, friends, and supporters in the United States. In particular, letters to women in supporting churches in the U.S. provide detailed accounts of Peggy's work in the field of women's education in Angola. Series IV includes various notes and published materials related to the Ovimbundu people and Umbundu language while Series V includes documentation related to the American Board of Commissioners for Foreign Missions work in Angola. Series VI includes writings of a missionary colleague, books about Angola, and samples of the wood of various Angolan trees that Duane Waln collected.
Arrangement
I. Writings of Duane V. Waln
II. Writings of Marian ("Peggy") Waln
III. Correspondence of Marian ("Peggy") Waln
IV. Ovimbundu/ Umbundu Materials
V. ABCFM Angola Mission Records
VI. Collected Materials
Mbundu (African people); Missions -- Angola; Umbundu language; Missionaries; Waln, Duane V.; Waln, Marian; American Board of Commissioners for Foreign Missions
- Writings of Duane V. Waln, Series I
  - Personal journals / diaries: 8 bound volumes, 1930-1941 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Personal journals / diaries: 5 bound volumes, 1942-1956 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Personal journals / diaries: 4 bound volumes, 1953-1962 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Thesis submitted for M.A., Kennedy School of Missions, Hartford Seminary, Department of Anthropology: "The Economic Life of the Ovimbundu", 1941 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Answers to exam questions: "Problems of the New Africa," "Women's Status in Africa," and "How Christianity Can Become a Way of Life for Africa", 1941, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Sketch of African church members and evangelists (in letter to Dr. D. Brewer Eddy), 1942 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Notebook of notes for talks (Box 4, Folder 8)
- Writings of Marian "Peggy" Waln, Series II
  - Personal stories of deaconesses and female church members (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Speech, "The Christian Women of Angola," on the event of the World Day of Prayer (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Typescript writings about Africa and the Angola mission (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Typescript writings about the missionary projects of the Chilesso Church (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - Typescript writings regarding the women's school and the educational program of mission schools in general (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - Typescript and holograph sketches of the life, inhabitants, and projects of Chilesso Station (Box 4, Folder 14)
- Correspondence of Marian "Peggy" Waln, Series III
  - Primarily to family members in U.S., from Angola, 1947-1952 (Box 4, Folder 15)
  - To family members and friends in the U.S, circular letter, letters re. mission accounts; from Angola, 1957 May-Aug (Box 4, Folder 16)
  - To/from family, friends, and supporters; to John Reuling, ABCFM, 1957 Aug-Sep (Box 4, Folder 17)
  - Primarily to/from family, friends, and supporters, 1957 Oct-1958 Jan (Box 4, Folder 18-19)
  - To family, friends, and supporters, 1958 Feb-Mar (Box 4, Folder 20-21)
  - Primarily to family, friends, and supporters, 1958 May (Box 4, Folder 22)
  - Primarily to family, friends, and supporters; to John Reuling, ABCFM, 1958 Jun (Box 4, Folder 23)
  - Primarily to family, friends, and supporters, 1958 Jul-Dec (Box 4, Folder 24-27)
  - To/from supporters, 1959 (Box 4, Folder 28)
  - Primarily to family, friends, and supporters, 1960 Jan-Mar (Box 4, Folder 29-31)
  - Primarily to family, friends, and supporters; to John Reuling, with enclosed description of her work, 1960 Apr (Box 5, Folder 32)
  - Primarily to family, friends, and supporters, 1960 May-1962 (Box 5, Folder 33-39)
- Ovimbundu/Umbundu Materials, Series IV
  - "Notes on the Ovimbundu of Andulo" by Duane Waln (Box 5, Folder 40)
  - "Ovimbundu Customs" by Duane Waln (Box 5, Folder 41)
  - Sketches of the lives of the Ovimbundu people of Chilesso Station (Box 5, Folder 42)
  - Umbundu-English dictionary, E to P (Box 5, Folder 43)
  - Umbundu-English dictionary, P to Y (Box 5, Folder 44)
  - English-Umbundu dictionary, A to H (Box 5, Folder 45)
  - English-Umbundu dictionary, H to Z (Box 5, Folder 46)
  - Misc. pages from an Umbundu-English dictionary, Waln's Umbundu grammar notes (Box 5, Folder 47)
  - Umbundu grammar (Box 5, Folder 49)
  - Umbundu Lessons: Book One (Box 5, Folder 50)
  - Umbundu Lessons: Book One (Box 6, Folder 51)
  - Hymnal in Portuguese and Umbundu, a biblical history in Umbundu, an edition of Pilgrim's Progress in Umbundu (Box 6, Folder 53)
  - "Popular Proverbs" in Umbundu and Portuguese and an Umbundu hymnal (Box 7, Folder 54)
- ABCFM Angola Mission Records, Series V
  - Misc. papers about Chilesso Station, an American Board publication about mission work in Angola (Box 7, Folder 55)
  - Chilesso Station diaries, 1905-1929, 1920-1949 (Box 7, Folder 56)
  - Currie Institute, Dondi - record of graduates 1914-1936 (Box 7, Folder 56a)
- Collected Materials, Six
  - Selected Writings by Leona Stukey Tucker (missionary to Angola) (Box 8, Folder 57)
  - Books about Angola and Portugal, arranged by author (Box 8, Folder 58)
  - Wood samples of Angolan trees collected by Duane V. Waln (Box 8, Folder 59)